Audella Beebe Hyatt Papers
Audella Beebe Hyatt Papers
1858-1957
Hyatt, Audella Beebe, 1840-1932.
7.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, incoming and outgoing (1860-1932); diaries; account books; notebooks; a partial autobiography; and sketches. Correspondents include Clara Carter Hyatt Coad, Mary E. Freeman, Anna Hyatt Huntington, Archer M. Huntington, Alpheus Hyatt, Leon Kroll, Alpheus Hyatt Mayor, and Harriet Randolph Hyatt Mayor.
149070
Biographical History
Audella Beebe Hyatt was born in Kinderhook, N.Y., on Feb. 14, 1840. Little is known of her early life. Her father was a farmer. Audella had a brother and sister four years older than herself, Aurelia, and together with their mother often traveled to New York City to buy new clothes. Audella attended a local academy for her education. Following the Civil War and the death of her father, she was living in New York with her mother when Mrs. Alpheus Hyatt of Baltimore asked her to come for a prolonged visit to Baltimore. Mrs. Hyatt (Harriet Randolph King) had recently become a widow. She and Audella had met during the war when they both were doing volunteer work. At the Hyatt estate, "Wansbec", Audella met Alpheus Hyatt II, and they were married Jan. 7, 1867. She had three children, Harriet, Alpheus III, and Anna Vaughn, a fourth child died in infancy.
Mrs. Hyatt was talented as an artist and painter of landscapes. She assisted her husband in his research by painting the sketches and diagrams for his books and lectures and copying his paleontological data. She moved with her husband to Cambridge, Mass. and made the Massachusetts area her home for more than thirty years.
She was also well known for her researches in family genealogy, the fruits of which placed with the work of her daughter Harriet are contained in the Hyatt-Mayor Genealogical Collection. Mrs. Hyatt had great wit and retained her charm until her death at the well-advanced age of 92.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers of Audella Beebe Hyatt (Mrs. Alpheus Hyatt II) include biographical material, extensive correspondence, account books, legal papers, notebooks, photographs, diaries, partial autobiography, sketches, and other manuscripts, and published material consisting of articles about others and newspaper clippings about Audella Hyatt and others.
Correspondence, includes both incoming and outgoing letters as well as the correspondence of others and correspondence arranged by subject consisting of a letterbook of sympathy letters dated 1879 and 1893, and a notebook of letters, mainly from Lizzie A. Hyatt Ogden. Correspondents include Clara Carter Hyatt Coad, Mary E. Freeman, Anna Hyatt Huntington, Archer M. Huntington, Alpheus Hyatt, Leon Kroll, Alpheus Hyatt Mayor, and Harriet Randolph Hyatt Mayor. Subject File, consists of account books, cards and invitations, legal papers, notes, notebooks, photographs and scrapbooks containing photographs, and scientific prints. Diaries, includes diaries arranged chronologically between the years 1858-1863, 1867, 1883, 1900-1905, 1907-1908, 1910, 1913, and one titled "Freiburg 1913-1914". Also included in this series is an undated diary. Manuscripts, includes an unorganized series of holograph notes and typed pages titled "Autobiography," a hand-drawn map titled "Battleground of Guildford Court House," and sketches. Published Material, includes articles about others, newspaper clippings about Audella Hyatt, and newspaper clippings about others.
Arrangement of the Collection
The incoming letters are arranged alphabetically by author. The outgoing letters are arranged chronologically. Subject File, Manuscripts, and Published Materials are arranged alphabetically by type.
Related Material
The has numerous collections for the Hyatt-Mayor families. For information on members of the Hyatt, Mayor, Beebe, and Huntington families see for the finding aids of individual family members.
Subject and Genre Headings
Freeman, Mary Eleanor Wilkins, 1852-1930.; Huntington, Anna Hyatt, 1876-1973.; Huntington, Archer Milton, 1870-; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902.; Hyatt, Audella Beebe, 1840-1932.; Kroll, Leon, 1884-1974.; Mayor, A. Hyatt (Alpheus Hyatt), 1901-; Mayor, Harriet Randolph Hyatt, 1868-1960.; Hyatt family.; Mayor family.; Art, American.; Painters -- United States.; Women artists -- United States.; Women painters -- United States.; Account books.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Sketches.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Anna Hyatt Huntington, 1964-1967.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - A - B (Box 1)
    - Beebe, William (Box 1)
    - Bergengren, Anna F. (Box 1)
    - C (Box 1)
    - Carter, Clara, See Coad, Clara Carter Hyatt
    - Coad, Clara Carter Hyatt
      - 1895 (Box 1)
      - 1896 (Box 1)
      - 1897 (Box 1)
      - 1898 (Box 1)
      - 1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1901 (Box 1)
      - 1902 (Box 1)
      - 1903 (Box 2)
      - 1904-1906 (Box 2)
      - 1907 (Box 2)
      - 1908 (Box 2)
      - Jan.-Jun. 1909 (Box 2)
      - Jul.-Nov. 1909 (Box 2)
      - 1910 (Box 2)
      - 1911 (Box 2)
      - 1915, 1916, 1918 (Box 2)
      - 1920, 1923-1929, 1931-1932 (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
      - Unidentified (Box 3)
    - D - E (Box 4)
    - F (Box 4)
    - Freeman, Mary E., "Dolly" (Box 4)
    - G (Box 4)
    - Glover, Mr. and Mrs. Alfred K. (Fannie) (Box 4)
    - H (Box 4)
    - Hodgdon, Clara Hyatt, See Kent, "Clarachen" Hyatt Hodgdon
    - Huntington, Anna V. Hyatt (Box 4)
    - Huntington, Archer M. (Box 4)
    - Hyatt, Alpheus II
      - 1870-1871, 1873, 1876, 1880 (Box 4)
      - 1881, 1883, 1885-1886 (Box 4)
      - 1887, 1889-1890 (Box 4)
      - 1891 (Box 4)
      - 1895-1896 (Box 4)
      - 1897-1898, 1900-1901 (Box 5)
      - Undated (Box 5)
      - Unidentified (Box 5)
    - Hyatt, Alpheus III
      - 1881, 1886-1887, 1891 (Box 5)
      - 1895-1897 (Box 5)
      - 1898-1905 (Box 5)
      - 1906-1910 (Box 5)
      - Undated (Box 5)
    - Hyatt, Amy (Box 5)
    - Hyatt, Anna Vaughn, See Huntington, Anna V. Hyatt
    - Hyatt, Clara Carter, See Coad, Clara Carter Hyatt
    - Hyatt, "Clarachen", See Kent, "Clarachen" Hyatt Hodgdon
    - Hyatt, Harriet (Daughter), See Mayor, Harriet Hyatt
    - Hyatt, Harriet R. (Mother-in-Law) (Box 5)
    - I - J (Box 5)
    - K (Box 5)
    - Kent, "Clarachen" Hyatt Hodgdon (Box 5)
    - Knoll, Leon (Box 5)
    - L (Box 6)
    - Linege, J. (Box 6)
    - Ludolf, Ernestine (Box 6)
    - M (Box 6)
    - Mayor, Alfred G. (Box 6)
    - Mayor, Alpheus Hyatt
      - 1917-1918 (Box 6)
      - 1919-1921 (Box 6)
      - 1922-1923 (Box 6)
      - 1924 (Box 6)
      - 1925-1926 (Box 6)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 6)
      - 1929-1932 (Box 6)
      - Undated (Box 6)
      - Undated (Box 6)
      - Undated (Box 6)
      - Unidentified (Box 6)
    - Mayor, Barbara, See Money, Barbara Mayor
    - Mayor, Brantz (Box 7)
    - Mayor, Harriet Hyatt
      - 1896-1899 (Box 7)
      - 1900 (Box 7)
      - Jan.-Feb. 1901 (Box 7)
      - Mar.-Apr. 1901 (Box 7)
      - May-Jun. 1901 (Box 7)
      - Sept.-Dec. 1901 (Box 7)
      - 1902 (Box 7)
      - 1903, 1906-1907, 1909, 1913-1916 (Box 8)
      - 1918-1919, 1925, 1927, 1929 (Box 8)
      - 1930-1932 (Box 8)
      - Undated (Box 8)
      - Undated (Box 8)
      - Unidentified (Box 8)
    - Mayor, Maria (Box 8)
    - Money, Barbara Mayor (Box 8)
    - Moore-Anderson, Nora (Box 8)
    - Motherling, Helen (Box 8)
    - N (Box 8)
    - P (Box 8)
    - R (Box 8)
    - Reynolds, Marian (Box 8)
    - S (Box 9)
    - Schutte, Alexander, 1863-1864 (Box 9)
    - Sisco, Claire (Box 9)
    - Stewart, Marie
      - Dated (Box 9)
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - T, V - W (Box 9)
    - Wilins, Mary "Dolly" Freeman, See Freeman, Mary E. "Dolly"
    - Unidentified (Box 9)
    - Unidentified, copies of letters (Box 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - 1853, 1862, 1867-1871 (Box 10)
    - 1885-1888 (Box 10)
    - 1903-1907 (Box 10)
    - 1909-1911 (Box 10)
    - 1922, 1924-1932 (Box 10)
    - Undated (Box 10)
    - Unidentified (Box 10)
    - Unidentified, copies of letters (Box 10)
  - Correspondence of others (Box 10)
  - Correspondence by Subject
    - Letterbook - Sympathy Letters, 1879; 1893 (Box 10)
    - Notebook of correspondence - mainly from Lizzie A. Hyatt Ogden (Box 10)
- Subject File
  - Account Book (Box 11)
  - Account Book (Box 11)
  - Cards and Invitations (Box 11)
  - Legal Papers (Box 11)
  - Notes (Box 11)
  - Notebooks (Box 11)
  - Notebooks (Box 11)
  - Photographs (Box 11)
  - Photographs - scrapbook (Box 12)
  - Photographs - scrapbook (Box 12)
  - Scientific Prints (Box 12)
- Diaries
  - 1858-1861 (Box 13)
  - 1862-1863 (Box 13)
  - 1867 (Box 13)
  - 1883 (Box 13)
  - 1900-1904 (Box 13)
  - 1905 (Box 14)
  - 1907-1908 (Box 14)
  - 1910 (Box 14)
  - 1913 (Box 14)
  - "Freiburg 1913-1914" (Box 14)
  - Undated (Box 14)
- Manuscripts
  - "Autobiography" (Box 15)
  - Map - "Battleground of Guilford Court House" (Box 15)
  - Sketches (Box 15)
- Published Material
  - Articles about others (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings about Audella Hyatt (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings about others (Box 15)